Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge Free And Accepted Masons Of Connecticut Records
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge Free And Accepted Masons Of Connecticut (Prince Hall Masons) Records.
undated, 1925-1987.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Bass, Floyd.; Pope, Preston L.; Bolden, Madison.; Fitch, Leroy.
6 linear feet.
The history of Black Free and Accepted Masons dates its origin from the initiation of Prince Hall on 6 March 1775 along with fourteen other free blacks into a Military Lodge of white masons. Lodge No. 441 of the Irish Registry up to the present time.
MSS19940061
History
Lodges were established in several areas of the American Colonies with the emigration of British Masons prior to the Revolutionary War. The American Revolution caused disruption in the firm establishment of a Grand Lodge in Connecticut until 1789. “The history of Black Free and Accepted Masons dates its origin from the initiation of Prince Hall on 6 March 1775 along with fourteen other free blacks into a Military Lodge of white masons. Lodge No. 441 of the Irish Registry up to the present time. Public acknowledgement of the legitimacy of black masonry came in March 1947 when the white Grand Lodge of Massachusetts officially recognized Prince Hall Masonry as a duly constituted regular and legitimate body. The committee of the white Grand Lodge of Massachusetts stated in its report regarding the charter issued to African Lodge in 1784, that it is believed to be the only original charter issued from the grand Lodge of England which is now in the possession of any lodge in America.” [Preamble to Biography of Prince Hall written by Preston L. Pope, 1975]
Scope and Content
The collection contains materials dating from 1925 through 1987, although the bulk of the collection dates from 1971-1981. The files are the result of a letter sent to several Grand Masters of the Lodge requesting their personal papers concerning freemasonry in Connecticut. Included in the collection is correspondence, reports, publications, photographs, addresses, lectures, ephemera and newspaper clippings all concerning the Lodge and its activities and members.
Arrangement
Series I:Grand Lodge Records ( undated, 1925-1987 )
Series II: Other Lodge Records ( undated, 1945-1984 )
Related Material
See also the Preston L. Pope Papers. For detailed information on the collections in Archives & Special Collections, please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Official Proceedings of the 165th and 166th Annual Communication,Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of Pennsylvania, 1980-1981. Dodd Periodicals
Official Proceedings of the 189th Annual Communication, Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of Massachusetts, 1980. Dodd Periodicals
Official Proceedings of the 116 Annual Communication, Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of Michigan, 1981. Dodd Periodicals
Official Proceedings of the 136th Annual Communication, Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of the State of New York, 1982. Dodd Periodicals
Official Proceedings of the 191st Annual Communication, Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of Massachusetts, 1982. Dodd Periodicals
Official Proceedings of the 115th Annual Communication, Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of the State of South Carolina, 1983. Dodd Periodicals
Official Proceedings of the 192nd Annual Communication, Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of Massachusetts, 1983. Dodd Periodicals
Official Proceedings of the 118th Annual Communication, Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of Michigan, 1983. Dodd Periodicals
Official Proceedings of the 135th Annual Communication, Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of Ohio, 1983-1984. Dodd Periodicals
Official Proceedings of the 136t Annual Communication, Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of Ohio, 1984-1985. Dodd Periodicals
Official Proceedings of the 194th Annual Communication, Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of Massachusetts, 1985. Dodd Periodicals
Official Proceedings of the 122nd Annual Communication, Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons for the State of Louisiana and Jurisdiction, 1986. Dodd Periodicals
Official Proceedings of the 123rd Annual Communication, Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons for the State of Louisiana and Jurisdiction, 1987. Dodd Periodicals
Two Hundred Years of Freemasonry in Connecticut. Case, James R. TGrand Lodge A.F. & A. M. of Connecticut, 1984.
Bibliography
Two Hundred Years of Freemasonry in Connecticut, James R. Case, 1984.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
Freemasons--Grand Lodge of Connecticut--Prince Hall Masons.
Subjects:
Freemansonry--Connecticut--history.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Photographs.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Press releases.; Manuscripts.
Occupations:
Free Masons.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The materials were collected from several Grand Masters of the Lodge.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Grand Lodge Records, undated, 1955-1987
  - Annual Convention, 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Booklets, 1925-1955 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Certificates, 1981 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Constitution, 1980 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Common Table, 1980 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Convention Artifacts, 1950-1970 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence
    - From Grand Master Preston L. Pope, undated, 1971-1987 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - To Grand Master Preston L. Pope, undated, 1974-1982 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Council of Deliberation Guidelines, 1980-1981 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Financial Report, 1973 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Lectures, undated, 1966, 1973 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper clippings and publications, 1958, 1972-1986 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Official Proceedings, 1962 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Official Proceedings, 1963 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Official Proceedings, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Official Proceedings, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - Official Proceedings, 1972 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Official Proceedings, 1973 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - Official Proceedings, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Order of the Eastern Star—Revised Charter, undated (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - Past Grand Masters, undated (Box 1:, Folder 21)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1:, Folder 22)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3:, Folder 48)
  - Prince Hall Biography, 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
  - Proclamations, 1975 (Box 2:, Folder 24)
  - Programs, 1959-1982 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
  - Reports, 1972-1981 (Box 2:, Folder 26)
  - Rogers, John (Dr.)
    - Bicentennial Plate, 1977 (Box 3:, Folder 47)
    - Certificates, undated, 1977 (Box 3:, Folder 49)
    - Portrait (Photograph), undated (Box OS)
  - Rosters, 1979-1984 (Box 2:, Folder 27)
- Series II: Other Lodges, undated, 1945-1984
  - Ashlar Lodge #19
    - Constitution and By-laws, undated (Box 2:, Folder 28)
  - Corinthian Lodge
    - By-laws, undated (Box 2:, Folder 29)
  - Dormant Lodges, undated (Box 2:, Folder 30)
  - Excelsior Lodge
    - Booklet, 1959 (Box 2:, Folder 31)
    - Certificate, 1957 (Box 3:, Folder 50)
    - Constitution, 1980 (Box 2:, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence to T. Ralph Watts, 1945-1978 (Box 2:, Folder 33)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1972-1973 (Box 2:, Folder 34)
  - George W. Crawford Lodge No. 21, undated (Box 2:, Folder 35)
  - Holy Royal Arch Masons
    - Common Table, undated (Box 2:, Folder 36)
    - Educational Bureau, 1984 (Box 2:, Folder 37)
    - Grand High Priest, undated (Box 2:, Folder 38)
    - Grand Master's Day, 1968 (Box 2:, Folder 39)
    - Heroines of Jericho, 1974-1975 (Box 2:, Folder 40)
    - Lectures, undated (Box 2:, Folder 41)
    - Preamble and History, undated, 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 42)
    - Proclamations and addresses, undated, 1971-1975 (Box 2:, Folder 43)
    - Roster, undated, 1973-1974, 1980-1981 (Box 2:, Folder 44)
  - Tuscan Brotherhood Homes, Inc., 1979 (Box 2:, Folder 45)
  - Widow's Son Lodge, 1981 (Box 2:, Folder 46)